Register of the Baltic Heritage Network collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Baltic Heritage Network collection
2002-2015
2006C57
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
The collection documents conferences held by the Baltic Heritage Network, an organziation linking archives and depositories internationally that are concerned with the history of the Estonian, Latvian, and Lithuanian diaspora. The collection consists of conference papers and abstracts, along with ephemera and printed matter relating to the history of the Baltic States, especially Estonia and Latvia.
Baltic Heritage Network
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by teh Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/ to find the full extent of the collection.
History Note
The first international conference dealing with archival holdings on the Baltic diaspora (the emigration from Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania during the twentieth century and its dispersed communities today) took place in Tartu, Estonia in June 2006. The meeting included historians and archivists from the Baltic States, Australia, Canada, Germany, the United States, and the Russian Federation; it was devoted to the presentation of papers, workshop meetings, and visits to a number of Estonian institutions whose collections related in some way to the subject of the conference. The the Baltic Heritage Network conferences have been held triennially: the first three in Tartu, with the fourth conference being held in Rīga, Latvia in 2015.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection documents conferences held by the Baltic Heritage Network, an organziation linking archives and depositories internationally that are concerned with the history of the Estonian, Latvian, and Lithuanian diaspora. The collection consists of conference papers and abstracts, along with ephemera and printed matter relating to the history of the Baltic States, especially Estonia and Latvia. There are also a number of brochures and pamphlets pertaining to museums, archives, and the National Library of Latvia. Additionally, there are some audiovisual materials in the collection, including a film and recorded music.
Arrangement
Arranged by document type.
Baltic States--Archival resources.
- Correspondence, 2006
  - General, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes call for papers, advance program, and list of participants
  - Noorhani, Piret, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 2)
- Papers, 2006
  - General, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 3)
    Includes abstracts of papers submitted prior to conference
  - Jacobs, David, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 4)
    Includes notes taken during conference sessions and subsequent report
- Final Memorandum, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 5)
  Includes earlier draft memorandum
- Conference Materials, 2002-2006
  - Program, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 6)
  - CD-ROM containing facsimiles of documents in the Estonian State Archives, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 7)
    Includes some printouts made subsequent to conference
  - Printed matter, 2002-2006
    - Announcement, brochures, card, reports, and serial issue, 2002-2006 (Text 1, Folder 8)
    - Monographs, 2006
      - Tagasi kodus/Back home, bilingual catalogue from an exhibition of documents at the National Archives of Estonia, 2002 (Text 1, Folder 9)
      - Suur põgenemine 1944: Eestlaste lahkumine läände ja selle mõjud, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 9)
        Study on the 1944 flight of Estonians to Western countries. In Estonian, with summary in English
- Other Printed Matter, 2004-2006
  Brochures, pamphlets, and printouts, largely relating to museums and archives in Tartu and Tallinn, 2004-2006. Printed copies
  - General, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 11)
  - Estonian History Museum, Tallinn, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 12)
    Contains information regarding an exhibit in Tallinn of photos from the 1905 Revolution in Estonia
  - Museum Dungeons of the KGB, Tartu, 2005 (Text 1, Folder 13)
    Includes postcard depicting the museum and its exhibits
  - Museum of Occupation and of the Fight for Freedom, Tallinn, 2004-2006 (Text 1, Folder 14)
    Includes facsimile re-edition of Estonian-Russian dictionary issued to Soviet troops prior to the USSR's 1940 annexation of the Baltic States
  - Journal article, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 15)
    Offprint of Tannberg, Tõnu and Enn Tarvel, "Documents on the Soviet Military Occupation of Estonia in 1940," TRAMES, vol. 10, no. 1, 2006. Printed copy
  - Serial issues, 2006
    - General, 2006 (Text 1, Folder 17)
      In Estonian, Russian, and English
    - General, 2006 (Text 2, Folder 1)
      In Russian
    - Akadeemia, no. 7, 2006 (Text 2, Folder 2)
      In Estonian with English abstracts
    - Paar Sammukest, no. 12, 2006 (Text 2, Folder 3)
      Issue of the journal of the Estonian Literary Museum containing articles on the 1905 Revolution in Estonia. In Estonian
- Photographs, 2006
  - 9 prints depicting museum exhibits in Tallinn, 2 prints of which depict paintings by Leonhard Lapin commenting on the Soviet occupation of Estonia and the 1939 Hitler-Stalin pact, 2006 (Text 2, Folder 4)
  - CD-ROM containing photographs from the conference, 2006 (Text 2, Folder 5)
- Increment, 2008-2015
  - Third conference of the Baltic Heritage Network, 2008-2012
    - Papers, 2012
      - Abstracts and program, 2012 (Text 3: 1)
      - Jacobs, David, "Hidden in Plain Sight: The History of the Baltic Diaspora in the Collections of the Hoover Institution Archives", 2012 (Text 3: 2)
        Includes two other related papers
    - Post-conference PowerPoint presentation, 2012 (Text 3: 3)
    - Printed matter, 2013
      - Article, 2013
        - Jacobs, David, "A Conference of the Baltic Heritage Network in Tartu, Estonia," Slavic & East European Information Resources, 14: 1, 2013 March 1 (Text 3: 4)
      - Monographs, 2007-2008
        Monographs include maps
        - Bleire, Daina and Jānis Riekstiņš, "The First Mass Deportation of the Inhabitants of Latvia: June 14, 1941", 2008 (Text #: 5, Text 3: 5)
        - Bleire, Dana and Jānis Riekstiņš, "The second mass deportation of the inhabitants of Latvia: March 25, 1949", 2008 (Text 3 :6, Text 3: 6)
  - Fourth conference of the Baltic Heritage Network, 2015
    - Invitation and program, 2015 (Text 3: 7)
    - Packet of materials given to participants, 2015 (Text 3: 8)
    - Papers, 2015
      - Abstracts, 2015 (Text 3: 9)
      - Jacobs, David, "Resources in the Hoover Institution Archives on the Search for Baltic Independence", 2015 June (Text 3: 10)
        Includes notes and draft of abstract
    - Membership list, 2015 (Text 3: 11)
    - Photographs, 2015 (Text 3: 12)
    - Printed matter, 2005-2015
      - Articles, 2015
        - Auzāne, Ilze, "Vektors un priekšu," Diena, 2015 June 30 (Text 3: 13)
        - Ciganovs, Juris, "Kauja par Tallinu," Klubs, 2015 January (Text 3: 14)
      - Monographs, 2005-2015
        - The Baltic Way and the Collapse of Totalitarian Communism: European Memory and Political Inspiration, 2015 (Text 3: 15)
        - Indāns, Ivars (ed.), Latvia and the United States: A New Chapter in Partnership, 2012 (Text 3: 16)
        - Pariks, Artis and Andis Kudors (eds.), The War in Ukraine: Lessons for Europe, 2015 (Text 3: 17)
        - Deksnis, Eduards Bruno and Tālavs Dundis, Resoration of Sovereignty and Independence of the Republic of Latvia 1986-1994, 2015 (Text 3: 18)
      - Newsletters, 2012-2015
        - Baltic Heritage Network, 2012-2015 (Text 4: 1)
      - Pamphlets, 2012-2015
        - Barrow, Maie, Estonians in Australia, 2012 (Text 4: 2)
        - No Baltijas ceļa līdz Gaismas pilij-Latvijas prezidentūra ES Padomē, 2015 (Text 4: 3)
      - Serial issues, 2015 June-August
        - Baltic Times, 2015 June-August (Text 4: 4)
        - Diena, 2015 June-July (Text 4: 5-6)
        - Riga This Week, 2015 July (Text 4: 7)
    - Register of participants, 2015 (Text 4: 8)
    - Subject file, 2015
      - Europeana Sounds, 2015 (Text 4: 9)
      - Museum of the Barrricades of 1991, 2015 (Text 4: 10)
      - National Library of Latvia, 2015 (Text 4: 11)
      - Rūndale Palace, 2015 (Text 4: 12)
    - Audiovisual materials, 2012-2015
      - DVD of "Class of 1943: Remember Us when We Are Gone," a film by Helga Marits
      - Two CDs and one DVD comprising "Siberi setode laulud-Songs of Siberian Seto", 2012 (Text 4: 15)
      - Two CDs comprising "Esto-Muusika: Ulgu-Eesti Leviplaadid, 1958-1998", 2015 (Text 4: 16)